<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:base="https://id.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/maechtekongresse/editions" xml:id="Verona_I_6.xml" prev="https://id.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/maechtekongresse/editions/Verona_I_5.xml" next="https://id.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/maechtekongresse/editions/Verona_I_7.xml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
<title type="main">Kongress von Verona</title> 
            <title type="main">I. Affaires d’Espagne</title>
            <title type="main">Denkschrift Wellingtons (Großbritannien)</title>
            <title type="sub">Digitale Edition</title>
            <editor>
               <persName>
                        <surname>Schneider</surname> <forename>Karin</forename></persName>
                </editor>
         <editor role="Technical_Editor">
    <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/13281899X">
        <surname>Kurz</surname>
        <forename>Stephan</forename></persName>
</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transkription</resp>
    <name ref="#KS">Karin Schneider</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Wissenschaftliche Edition</resp>
    <name ref="#KS">Karin Schneider</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
    <name ref="#SK">Stephan Kurz</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Korrekturen</resp>
<name ref="#KS">Karin Schneider</name>
    <name ref="#SK">Stephan Kurz</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Beratung Kodierung</resp>
    <name>Daniel Schopper</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Beratung Kodierung</resp>
    <name>Peter Andorfer</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
                    <date>2017-03-13</date>
                </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Österreichische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Institut für Neuzeit- und
               Zeitgeschichtsforschung</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Wien</pubPlace>
<date when="2018-09-23" change="#initial">2018-09-23</date>
            <idno>V_I_06</idno>
                <idno type="ISBN" n="9783950478303">978-3-9504783-0-3</idno>
                 <availability>           <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/legalcode.de">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/legalcode.de</licence>         </availability> <tei:idno xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="handle">http://hdl.handle.net/21.11115/0000-000C-1F03-F</tei:idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
    <note>Vergleiche auch die Projektbeschreibung in der <ref type="URI" target="../meta/Einleitung.xml">Einleitung</ref> sowie die Dokumentation der Applikation unter <ref type="URI" target="../meta/about.xml">„Über diese Webseite“</ref>.</note>
</notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="m.1" type="Lithographie">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>Wien</settlement>
                  <institution>ÖStA</institution>
                  <collection>HHStA, Staatskanzlei, Kongressakten</collection>
                  <idno>
                     <idno type="Karton">Kart. 23</idno>
                     <idno type="Faszikel"> Fasz. 43 (alt)</idno>
                     <idno type="Folia">134–143</idno>
                  </idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <title>Denkschrift Wellingtons (Großbritannien)</title>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Lithographie</p>
                  <p>Das Schriftstück liegt in der englischen Originalfassung zweifach auf fol.
                     134–137 (Lithographie) und fol. 138–143 (handschriftlich) ein. Die
                     Transkription folgt der Fassung auf fol. 134–137. Eine französische Übersetzung
                     von der Hand <persName ref="#p.5">
                                <surname>Gentz</surname></persName> liegt auf
                     fol. 133 und 144–146 ein, eine Lithographie der französischen Übersetzung
                     findet sich auf fol. 132 und 147–148. Vermerk mit Bleistift in der rechten
                     oberen Ecke von fol. 132r: <q>No. 6.</q>
                        </p>

                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote xml:id="A">Anonyme Hand</handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="A1">Weitere anonyme Hand</handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="G">Friedrich Gentz</handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="W">Nikolaus Wacken</handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="AmB">Anonyme Hand mit Bleistift</handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="AmR">Anonyme Hand mit Rotstift</handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="M">Metternich</handNote>
                  </handDesc>

               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                            <placeName ref="#loc.68">Verona</placeName>
                            <date when="1822-10-30">30.
                        Oktober 1822</date>
                        </origin>
               </history>
            </msDesc>
            <listWit corresp="#m.1">
               <head>Denkschrift Wellingtons (Großbritannien)</head>
               <witness corresp="#w.5">
                        <bibl type="print">BFSP, 1822–1823, S. 6–8;</bibl>
                    </witness>
               <witness corresp="#w.17">
                        <bibl type="print">Clarke, Papers presented to parliament
                     1823, S. 26–30.</bibl>
                    </witness>
            </listWit>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <appInfo>
            <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
               <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
            </application>
         </appInfo>
         <styleDefDecl scheme="css"/>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="su" scheme="css">vertical-align:super; font-size:.7em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="s" scheme="css">text-decoration:line-through;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="u" scheme="css">text-decoration:underline;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="ow" scheme="css">text-decoration:line-through;text-decoration-style:double;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p>Im Auftrag seiner Regierung rät der britische Gesandte <persName ref="#p.10">
                        <surname>Wellington</surname></persName> von jeglicher Intervention in
                  <country>Spanien</country> ab und geht nicht weiter auf die in der <ref target="Verona_I_2.xml">Denkschrift der französischen Regierung aufgeworfenen
                  Fragen</ref> ein.</p>
         </abstract>
      </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
    <change xml:id="initial" when="2018-09-23" who="#SK">initial version for public beta release</change>
    <change notAfter="2018-09-23" who="#SK #KS">changetracking on ACDH git repository</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div decls="#m.1">
            <pb n="134r"/>
            <p>Since the month of April 1820, the British Government have availed themselves of
               every opportunity of recommending to <rs ref="#p.130" type="person">His Majesty</rs>’s Allies to
               abstain from all interference in the internal affairs of
               <country>Spain</country>.</p>
            <p>Without adverting to those principles which His Majesty’s Government must always
               consider the rule of their conduct in relation to the internal Affairs of other
               Countries, they considered that to whatever degree either the origin of <rs xml:id="n.1">the Spanish revolution</rs>,<note type="editorial" target="#n.1">Zur
                  Revolution in <country>Spanien</country>, die mit einem Militäraufstand am <date when="1820-01-01">1. Jänner 1820</date> ihren Anfang nahm, vgl. Späth,
                  Revolution in Europa, S. 117–128. In Portugal war am 24. August 1820 eine
                  Revolution ausgebrochen; vgl. Birmingham, A Concise History, S. 111–113. </note>
               the system then established, or the conduct of those who have since had the
               management of the internal Affairs of <country>Spain</country> might be disapproved
               of, any amelioration, which might be desired in the Spanish system, for the sake of
                  <country>Spain</country> Herself, ought to be sought for in measures to be adopted
               in <country>Spain</country>, rather than abroad, and particularly in the confidence
               which the people should be taught to feel in the Character and measures of the <rs ref="#p.30" type="person">King</rs>.</p>
            <p>They considered that an interference with a view to assist the Monarch on the throne,
               to overturn that which had been settled, and which he had guaranteed, or to promote
               the establishement<pb n="134v"/> of any other form of Government or Constitution,
               particularly by force, would only place that Monarch in a false position, and prevent
               him from looking to the internal means of amelioration which might be within His
               reach.</p>
            <p>Such an interference always appeared to the British Government an unnecessary
               assumption of responsibility which, considering all the circumstances, must expose
               the <rs ref="#p.30" type="person">King of Spain</rs> to danger, and the power or powers which
               should interfere, to obloquy, certain risks, and possible disasters to enormous
               expences, and final disappointement in producing any result.</p>
            <p>Upon these principles <rs ref="#p.130" type="person">His Majesty</rs> has advised His Allies, and
               has acted Himself, from the month of April 1820, to the present day.</p>
            <p>
                    <rs ref="#t.42" type="treaties">The Protocoles and other Acts of the Congress at <placeName ref="#loc.1">Aix-la-Chapelle</placeName>, which established the union at
                  present existing between the five powers so happily for the world,</rs> require
               the most unlimited confidence and communication on the part of Each; and accordingly
                  <rs ref="#p.130" type="person">His Majesty</rs> has never failed to communicate to His Allies,
               and particularly to <country>France</country>, every instruction which he has sent to
                  <rs ref="#p.146" type="person">His Minister at <placeName ref="#loc.24">Madrid</placeName></rs>,
               and all the communications made by <rs ref="#p.130" type="person">His Majesty</rs>’s commands to
               the <rs ref="#p.176" type="person">Minister of Spain residing<pb n="135r"/> in <placeName ref="#loc.8">London</placeName></rs>; all in the same spirit of good will
               towards the <rs ref="#p.30" type="person">King of Spain</rs> and the Spanish Nation.</p>
            <p>It is impossible to look at the existing relations between <country>France</country>
               and <country>Spain</country> without adverting to what has passed from the
               commencement of the year 1820 to the present moment, and without being sensible of
               the unfortunately false position in which the <rs ref="#p.30" type="person">King of Spain</rs> is
               placed, and that the spirit of party in both countries, having aggravated the
               national antipathy which antecedent circumstances had occasioned, is in a great
               measure the cause of the unfortunate Irritation in <country>Spain</country> against
                  <country>France</country>, to which his Excellency the <rs ref="#p.174" type="person">Minister
                  of France</rs> has adverted.</p>
            <p>The great object of <rs ref="#p.130" type="person">His Majesty</rs>’s Foreign policy is to preserve
               peace among Nations, and He feels the most anxious interest for the happiness of <rs ref="#p.15" type="person" xml:id="n.2">His most Christian Majesty</rs>
                    <note type="editorial" target="#n.2">Ehrentitel des Königs von Frankreich. </note> and the honour of His
               Government, and it would be His sincere desire to allay that irritation, but His
               government cannot but feel that, to make any declaration on any of the three points
               referred to by <rs ref="#p.174" type="person">His Excellency</rs>, without a previous accurate
               knowledge of all the circumstances which have occured between the<pb n="135v"/> two
               Countries, would be not only premature and unjust, but would probably be unavailing,
               and would in fact deprive <rs ref="#p.130" type="person">His Majesty</rs> of the power of
               discussing and deciding upon the measures of his own Government in this Affair
               hereafter, when he should be better informed.</p>
            <p>
                    <rs ref="#p.130" type="person">His Majesty</rs> must either place Himself in this painful and
               inconsistent position for an independent Sovereign, or he must do what would be
               equally painful to His feelings, require from His August Friend and Ally the <rs ref="#p.15" type="person">King of France</rs>, that He should submit his conduct to the advice
               and control of His Majesty.</p>
            <p>His Majesty’s Government cannot think either alternative to be necessary, but are of
               opinion, that a review of the obvious circumstances of the situation of
                  <country>France</country>, as well as of <country>Spain</country>, will shew that,
               whatever may be the tone assumed towards <country>France</country> by the ruling
               Powers in <country>Spain</country>, they are not in a state to carry into execution
               any plan of real hostility or injury.</p>
            <p>Considering that a civil war exists in the whole extent of the Frontier which
               separates the two Kingdoms, that hostile Armies are in movement and in operation
                  on<pb n="136r"/> every part of it, and that there is not a town or village on the
               French frontiers which is not liable to insult and injury, there is no person who
               must not approve of the precaution which <rs ref="#p.15" type="person">
                        <choice>
                     <abbr>H. M. C. M.</abbr>
                     <expan>His Most Christian Majesty</expan>
                  </choice></rs> has taken in forming a Corps of observation for the protection of
               His frontier, and for the <unclear>preservation</unclear> of the tranquillity of His
               people. <rs ref="#p.130" type="person">
                        <choice>
                     <abbr>H. B. M</abbr>
                     <expan>His British Majesty</expan>
                  </choice></rs> sincerely wishes that this measure may be effectual in attaining
               the objects for which it is calculated, and that the wisdom of the French Government
               will have induced them to explain it at <placeName ref="#loc.24">Madrid</placeName>,
               in such terms as will satisfy the Government of His
                  Catholic Majesty of its necessity.</p>
            <p>Such an explanation will, it is hoped, tend to allay in some degree the irritation
               against <country>France</country>; and, on the other hand, it may be hoped that some
               allowance will be made in <country>France</country> for the state of effervescence of
               Men’s Minds in Spain, in the very Crisis of a revolution and civil war.</p>
            <p>A moments reflection upon the relative power of the two States will shew, that the
               real Evil to which <rs ref="#p.15" type="person">
                        <choice>
                     <abbr>H. M. C. M.</abbr>
                     <expan>His Most Christian Majesty</expan>
                  </choice></rs> is exposed, is that resulting from the operations of the civil war
               on the neighbouring Frontier of <country>Spain</country>, against which the measure
               which His Government have adopted is best calculated to preserve Him. Even
               revolutionary madness could not calculate<pb n="136v"/> upon the success of a serious
               attack by <country>Spain</country> upon <country>France</country>, under any
               circumstances which it is possible to suppose to exist at present in the latter
               kingdom. But the attention of the Spanish Government is now occupied by a civil war,
               the operations of which certainly justify the formation of a Corps of observation in
                  <country>France</country>; and it is not very probable that they would, at this
               moment, desire to break with <country>France</country>. Neither is it to be believed
               that, in their present situation, they would not desire still to enjoy the advantage
               of that countenance to their system, which the presence of the French Ambassador at
               the seat of Government must afford them.</p>
            <p>
                    <rs ref="#p.130" type="person">His Majesty</rs> therefore considers any rupture by
                  <country>Spain</country>, or any measure on her part which may render necessary
               the immediate discontinuance of diplomatic Relations by <country>France</country>,
               very improbable, and as <rs ref="#p.130" type="person">His Majesty</rs> is quite unacquainted with
               what has passed between <country>France</country> and <country>Spain</country> since
               the month of April 1820, and His Government cannot know upon what grounds <rs ref="#p.15" type="person">His Most Christian Majesty</rs>’s Government may think proper to
               discontinue the diplomatic relations of <country>France</country> with
                  <country>Spain</country>, or upon what grounds war may break out between the two
               countries, it is impossible for them now to pronounce what<pb n="137r"/> advice they
               should consider it their duty to give to <rs ref="#p.130" type="person">His Majesty</rs>, in case
               either or both of those events should occur.</p>
            <p>
                    <rs ref="#p.130" type="person">His Majesty</rs> most anxiously wishes that such extremities may be
               avoided, and He feels convinced that the Government of <rs ref="#p.15" type="person">His Most <choice>
                     <abbr>Chr.</abbr>
                     <expan>Christian</expan>
                  </choice> Majesty</rs> will find means of avoiding them.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      
   
    <back>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="p.5">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Friedrich</forename>
                        <surname>Gentz</surname></persName>
                    <birth>1764</birth>
                    <death>1832</death>
                    <note>Protokollführer; vgl. zu seiner Person Kronenbitter, Wort und Macht;
                        Cahen, Gentz; Mann, Friedrich von Gentz; Schneider, Werner, Europa in Wien,
                        S. 169–170.</note>
                    <idno type="URI">https://viaf.org/viaf/2522018/</idno>
                <idno type="GND">http://d-nb.info/gnd/118538489/</idno></person>
                <person xml:id="p.10">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Arthur</forename>
                        <surname>Wellesley</surname>, <roleName>1<hi rendition="#su">st</hi> duke of
                            Wellington</roleName></persName>
                    <birth>1769</birth>
                    <death>1852</death>
                    <note>Bevollmächtigter Großbritanniens; vgl. zu seiner Person zuletzt Muir,
                        Wellington; Gash, Wellesley, Arthur, first duke of Wellington. In: ODNB, Bd.
                        58, S. 1–29.</note>
                    <idno type="URI">https://viaf.org/viaf/2465308/</idno>
                <idno type="GND">http://d-nb.info/gnd/118806645/</idno></person>
                <person xml:id="p.130">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>George IV.</surname>
                        <roleName>König des Vereinigten Königreichs Großbritannien und Irland, König
                            von Hannover</roleName></persName>
                    <birth>1762</birth>
                    <death>1830</death>
                    <note>Zwischen 1811 und 1820 Prinzregent; vgl. zu seiner Person Hibbert, George
                        IV. In: ODNB, Bd. 21, S. 856–864; Smith, George IV.</note>
                    <idno type="URI">https://viaf.org/viaf/265481029/</idno>
                <idno type="GND">http://d-nb.info/gnd/118690450/</idno></person>
                <person xml:id="p.30">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Ferdinand/Fernando VII.</surname>
                        <roleName>König von Spanien</roleName></persName>
                    <birth>1784</birth>
                    <death>1833</death>
                    <note>Vgl. zu seiner Person Sánchez Mantero, Fernando VII.</note>
                    <idno type="URI">https://viaf.org/viaf/286447916/</idno>
                <idno type="GND">http://d-nb.info/gnd/119307421/</idno></person>
                <person xml:id="p.146">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>William</forename>
                        <surname>A’Court</surname>
                        <roleName>1<hi rendition="#su">st</hi> Baron Heytesbury</roleName></persName>
                    <birth>1779</birth>
                    <death>1860</death>
                    <note>1820 britischer Botschafter in Neapel, 1822 britischer Botschafter in
                        Madrid; vgl. zu seiner Person Chamberlain, A’Court, William, first Baron
                        Heytesbury. In: ODNB, Bd. 1, S. 162–163.</note>
                    <idno type="URI">http://viaf.org/viaf/315945654/</idno>
                <idno type="GND">http://d-nb.info/gnd/1146859546/</idno></person>
                <person xml:id="p.176">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Juan Gabriel</forename>
                        <surname>Jabat Aztal</surname></persName>
                    <birth>1768</birth>
                    <death>1825</death>
                    <note>Ab März 1822 spanischer Gesander in London; vgl. <ref target="http://dbe.rah.es/biografias/15293/juan-gabriel-jabat-aztal">http://dbe.rah.es/biografias/15293/juan-gabriel-jabat-aztal</ref>
                    </note></person>
                <person xml:id="p.174">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Mathieu Jean Félicité</forename>
                        <roleName>Vicomte</roleName>
                        <surname>de Montmorency-Laval</surname></persName>
                    <birth>1766</birth>
                    <death>1826</death>
                    <note>1821/22 französischer Außenminister, Vertreter Frankreichs auf dem
                        Kongress von Verona; vgl. zu seiner Person Michaud, Biographie universelle,
                        Bd. 29, S. 181-183.</note>
                    <idno type="URI">https://viaf.org/viaf/66610110/</idno>
                <idno type="GND">http://d-nb.info/gnd/104256060/</idno></person>
                <person xml:id="p.15">
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Ludwig/Louis XVIII.</surname>
                        <roleName> König von Frankreich</roleName></persName>
                    <birth>1755</birth>
                    <death>1824</death>
                    <note>Vgl. Malettke, Die Bourbonen; Thamer, Ludwig XVIII.; Mansel, Louis
                        XVIII.</note>
                    <idno type="URI">https://viaf.org/viaf/84035484/</idno>
                <idno type="GND">http://d-nb.info/gnd/118780743/</idno></person>
            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place xml:id="loc.68">
               <placeName>Verona</placeName>
                <placeName>Vérone</placeName>
               <location>
                        <geo>45.4299 10.98444</geo>
                    </location>
                    <idno type="URI">https://www.geonames.org/3164527</idno>
            </place>
                <place xml:id="loc.1">
                <placeName>Aachen</placeName>
               <placeName>Aix-la-Chapelle</placeName>
               
               <location>
                        <geo>50.77664 6.08342</geo>
                    </location>
                    <idno type="URI">https://www.geonames.org/3247449</idno>
            </place>
                <place xml:id="loc.24">
               <placeName>Madrid</placeName>
               <location>
                        <geo>40.4165 -3.70256</geo>
                    </location>
                    <idno type="URI">https://www.geonames.org/3117735</idno>
            </place>
                <place xml:id="loc.8">
                <placeName>London</placeName>
               <placeName>Londres</placeName>
               
               <location>
                        <geo>51.50853 -0.12574</geo>
                    </location>
                    <idno type="URI">https://www.geonames.org/2643743</idno>
            </place>
            </listPlace>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="t.42">Protokoll, Aachen 15. November 1818, mit welchem Frankreich wieder
               in das Konzert der Mächte aufgenommen wird, sowie die entsprechende Deklaration;
               vgl. für das Protokoll Meyer, Staats-Acten, S. 275–276; Grewe, Fontes, Bd. 3/1, S.
               104–106; de Clercq, Recueil, Bd. 3, S. 175–176; BFSP Bd. 6 (1818/19), S. 14–15;
               Angeberg, Congrès, Bd. 3, S. 1755–1756; Näf (Hg.) Europapolitik, S. 22–23, Bertier de
               Sauvigny, Sainte-Alliance, S. 148–150, für die Deklaration BFSP Bd. 6 (1818/19), S.
               18–20; de Clercq, Recueil, Bd. 3, S. 179–181; Angeberg, Congrès, Bd. 3, S. 1760–1761;
               Meyer, Staats-Acten, S. 276–278; Näf (Hg.) Europapolitik, S. 23–25, Bertier de
               Sauvigny, Sainte-Alliance, S. 163–164.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>